The next organization that we will be
looking at is similar to distributed
shared memory except that we are no
longer sharing memory. So it's called
distributed memory. No sharing of memory
means that only one core can access a
memory slice and the others cannot. So
what we now have is cores that have
their own caches and each of them has
its own memory that can only be locally
accessed here. So really each of the
core has pretty much what looks like a
complete single core computer system and
a network interface card that connects
it to a network. But now when a cork has
a cache miss that cache miss goes
directly to this memory and if the core
wants to access something that is in
another core's memory it cannot simply
issue an access that misses in the cache
and goes there. Now what it needs to do
is actually create a network message
using some sort of a send primitive in
the operating system to actually send a
request. The program here needs to
receive that, see what is being
requested, respond to it and so on. So
now communication is explicit. It's no
longer sufficient to simply put the data
in memory and then another core just
reads it from there. you have to
actually send the data explicitly to
another core if we want to communicate.
So that means that you write programs
differently from this symmetric shared
memory and distributed shared memory
pass data around using shared memory
meaning reads and writes to memory are
used to exchange data. Now we are using
what is called message passing for
communication. So now you're pretty much
writing a program as if these were
independent machines that communicate
over a network. If you have a
distributed memory supercomput for
example, it's just that this network and
these network cards are a lot faster
than your normal Ethernet connection.
This type of a system is also called a
multicomput because really each of these
is like a complete computer. It has the
processor, the cache, the memory, some
IO and the processor only directly
accesses the local memory. So it looks
like a complete uni processor system.
These are also called cluster computers
because really you put a bunch of normal
computers together into a tightly
network cluster and you get something
like a distributed memory system. These
types of
computers tend to scale to a large
number of processors. The reason is not
that they're fundamentally better at
communicating than shared memory
systems. The reason is mainly that the
programmer is forced to explicitly think
about communication because you use a
different type of primitive to
communicate than you use to access your
local memory. So the programmer is aware
of communication going on and then
naturally they will tend to minimize
communication and if at all possible
access the local memory. So this
approach works better primarily because
it forces the programmer to figure out
things that otherwise it might not
notice because it forces the programmer
to figure out how to communicate
efficiently. Whereas in shared memory,
the programmer may not even realize that
some of the luxes are not local and thus
are slow and causing a lot of
communication to happen.